<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE book PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN"
"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd">
<chapter id="JCR.AdvantagesOfeXoJCR">
  <?dbhtml filename="ch-jcr-advantages.html"?>
  <title>Advantages of eXo JCR</title>

  <section>
    <title>Advantages for application developers:</title>

    <para>* Data repository and application are isolated from each other so an
    application developer should not learn the details of particular data
    storage's interfaces and can concentrate on business logic of a particular
    application built on top of JCR</para>

    <para>* Repositories can be simply exchanged between different
    applications without changing the applications themselves. This is the
    matter of the repository configuration</para>

    <para>* Data storage types/versions can be changed and moreover different
    types of data storages can be combined in one repository data model (of
    course the complexity and work of building interfaces between the
    repository and its data storage don't disappear but these changes are
    isolated in the repository and thus manageable from the point of view of
    the customer)</para>

    <mediaobject>
      <imageobject>
        <imagedata fileref="images/concepts/jcr-490x333.gif" />
      </imageobject>
    </mediaobject>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Advantages for managers</title>

    <para>* Using a standardized repository for content management reduces the
    risk of being dependent on a particular software vendor and proprietary
    API.</para>

    <para>* Costs for maintaining and developing a content repository based
    custom application is significantly lower than developing and supporting
    your own interfaces and maintaining your own data repository applications
    (staff can be trained once, it is possible to take help from community and
    third party consulters).</para>

    <para>* Thanks to flexible layered JCR API (see below) it is possible to
    fit the legacy storage subsystem into new interfaces and again decrease
    the costs and risk of losing data.</para>

    <para>An extension to the API exists as we can see in the following layer
    schema.</para>

    <mediaobject>
      <imageobject>
        <imagedata fileref="images/concepts/JCR-Application2.jpg" />
      </imageobject>
    </mediaobject>
  </section>
</chapter>
